A Guide to the Ellen Wayles Randolph Coolidge Correspondence 1810-1861
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Autobiographical Writings of Ellen Coolidge 1828 June 15-July 13 (Box 2)
  she discusses how her unique background and education did not prepare her for the normal adversity experienced in life, mentions the influence of good books and "the very perfect characters of my grandfather and mother always before my eyes, [which] gave me a high standard of moral and intellectual worth with which perpetually to compare myself," her reflections concerning the danger of personal anger and the necessity for energy in all of life's tasks, agreeable or not
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1828 June 24 (Box 2)
  mentions her concern over the news of her father's illness, Joseph's financial difficulties, George's account with his teacher Mr. Wells, Allston's confirmation of the judgement of the other appraisers as to the value of the paintings and their ruinous state, and informs the family that Joseph does not wish to purchase a Virginia horse
- Martha Randolph to George Wythe Randolph 1828 June 30 (Box 2)
  sends news of his father's last illness and death, his reconciliation with all of the family, even Jefferson, and their attention to him in his last days, her advice as to good habits in youth, news that Monticello will be sold this fall with the remaining property of the family, and her uncertainty of where she will live
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1828 June [30?] (Box 2)
  recounts the reconciliation of Jeff and his father who sent for him while on his deathbed, John Hemings took the message, Randolph asked forgiveness of the whole family and admitted he followed his passion rather than his head
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1828 July 6-8 (Box 2)
  furnishes details about the illness and death of her father, the sickness and death of Aunt Marks, reflections upon their afflictions, describes Monticello with its wild growth in the yard and the unpruned trees, compares her feelings on Monticello being sold to that of profaning a temple, mentions that Martha is considering living in Philadelphia, and mentions Julia Maria Dickenson Tayloe's autograph album of great men of America
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1828 July 20 (Box 2)
  describes some of the delegates to the Virginia Convention, James Monroe, James Madison, Justice Marshall, the argument between Charles Fenton Mercer and Chapman Johnson, the meeting of the Board of Visitors, and Mrs. Madison's suggestion of living in Washington
- A fragment addressed to Joseph Coolidge 1828 July 21 (Box 2)
  concerns the death of Thomas Mann Randolph, noting that his absence was not a source of permanent grief
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1828] August 7 (Box 2)
  strongly urges Nicholas and his family to seek their fortune in Washington by cashing in on the obligations of the nation to the heirs of a President of the United States and to contact influential friends of the family for a position in government, gives bad news concerning the sale of the paintings from Monticello, since so far only the Benjamin Franklin had been sold to the Boston Athenaeum but promises to continue to try selling the others, comments upon the building activity in Boston, and the prosperity of the Athenaeum
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1828 August 10 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the prevalence of the measles and dysentery in the Charlottesville vicinity, three deaths at the University due to illness, an alteration in one of the rooms at Monticello once containing Thomas Jefferson's books by filling up the smaller of two arches and making a sleeping room, Jeff's uncertainty about whether Monticello could be sold or rented, and Mrs. Dunglison staying at Monticello to isolate her children from the measles
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1828 August 19 (Box 2)
  mentions news of Boston, her domestic staff, the marriage of Thomas Coolidge, Joseph's brother who will live at the old Coolidge house temporarily, and the difference in the reception given the new bride with her own
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1828 September 3 (Box 2)
  relates her opinion of French opera singers in Boston, the social error of Mrs. Thomas Coolidge (the former Miss Goldsborough) committed while in the opera box and the full band playing on the Boston Common two nights a week
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1828 October 28 (Box 2)
  asks about the news of an appointment for Nicholas secured by Henry Clay, expresses her concern for George's progress at school, and tells her mother that the painting of Franklin sold by Joseph has paid all of George's expenses
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1828 December 29 (Box 2)
  announces the birth of Joseph Randolph Coolidge to Ellen and himself, and gives the amount received for the painting of Franklin as two hundred dollars and one hundred for a Lafayette
- A Copy of the Epitaph of Thomas Mann Randolph by [Ellen Coolidge] [1828?] (Box 2)
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1829 January 1 (Box 2)
  mentions problems with naming his son, financial failures in Boston, Boston politics, an attempt to put a Mr. Ticknor in as president of Harvard College, the lighting of the streets of Boston with gas lamps, and advice to Nicholas to sell his share in the Charlottesville Virginia Advocate
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1829 January 12 (Box 2)
  writes more concerning Harvard College politics, his approval of Nicholas' plans to move to Washington, and the safe arrival of the violins in England to be sold
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge 1829 January 25 (Box 2)
  while on a visit to Carysbrook she writes of her plans to visit more during the winter to relieve Jeff of the burden of her large family as much as possible, the possibility that Nicholas may get rid of the paper without much loss, the hiring of a dining room servant from Virginia Randolph Cary (1786-1852) for a year by Nicholas, and the success of Cary's books, Letters on Female Character Addressed to a Young Lady on the Death of her Mother and Christian Parent's Assistant, or Tales, for the Moral and Religious Instruction of Youth
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1829 March 3 (Box 2)
  relates her difficulties in securing, keeping, and training good domestic staff which she refers to in Boston as "stiff-necked hard mouthed democrats," her conclusion that it is a wearisome thing to be a woman, and her fears that her own children will have no one to care for them since her family is so removed from Boston
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1829 April 26 (Box 2)
  sends news of her children's health, the failure of several Boston businessmen, Samuel Perkins, John Rogers, and Charles Toney, the welfare of George, Joseph's desire to own the Natural Bridge and an inquiry to Jeff as to its value
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1829 May 3 (Box 2)
  bemoans her lack of useful qualities, and says she has been "pawning my jewels to procure my linen," describes her own religious belief in detail and her own particular form of Unitarianism, and gives her advice on economy
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge 1829 May 12 (Box 2)
  writes concerning family sickness, Nicholas Trist's house at the second cross street west of the President's house with enough room for a garden, fruit trees, the intention of Browse Trist to live there as well, and the progress in the revision of Thomas Jefferson's papers for the publication of Memoir, Correspondence, and Miscellany
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge [1829] May 28 (Box 2)
  writes concerning their busy schedule in revising and correcting the copies of the manuscripts of Jefferson's papers, at ten hours work a day she estimates they will finish in July unless the three volumes of the Anas will be included, the weakness of Ben, the request of Burwell S. Randolph to be admitted to the family contributing the same amount to the general fund as Browse, and the details of her plan to raise the extra money needed to move and set up housekeeping in Washington
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1829 June 21 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the boarding of their children in the countryside for the summer to help their health, advice to her mother for economizing, and describes the trial involving the suit between the heirs of Tuttle Hubbard and Peter C. Brooks, with William Wirt and Webster opposing each other
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1829 July 21 (Box 2)
  describes the visit of one of Nicholas' roguish friends to Boston society at the Coolidge home, the hiring of a French cook for a special meal, the businesses failing in Boston, bankruptcy of Cornelius Coolidge, and her disapproval of Frances Wright (1795-1852) an early American feminist reformer and publisher of Free Enquirer and her lover Robert Dale Owen, when she arrived in Boston to give a course of lectures
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1829 August 12 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the completion of their work on Jefferson's papers for publication, news of the extended family, especially the Ashton family at Lynchburg, the plan to pack up their furniture at Monticello to go to Washington, and a long paragraph concerning her impressions of the charm that surrounds Monticello and the advantages of its high elevation
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1829 August 23 (Box 2)
  sends news of Jane's advancing pregnancy, Virginia's impatience at being separated from her husband, and her dislike of Ben Rice's sermon attacking the doctrine of the Unitarians, which was delivered as a result of the minister reading a copy of Jefferson's letter to John Adams concerning his views on religion in Memoir and Correspondence
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1829 August 31 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the birth of Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Jeff and Jane, the health of Jane, a mid-October date of departure for Washington, John Hemings help in preparing to leave Monticello, Dr. William Bankhead's marriage and offer to take Willie Bankhead, Anne's son, to live with him, Jeff's promise to send copies of each volume of Jefferson's papers as they are published to Joseph, Jeff's plan to run for the Virginia Assembly at which Jane is extremely angry, and Martha calls the Assembly "a paltry business"
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1829 October 25 (Box 2)
  describes her last visit to the University and its library, her farewell visits to friends, Benjamin's work as the subscription collection agent for the works of Thomas Jefferson to pay his fees at the University where he will study to become a doctor, the marriage of Dr. Johnson at the University to Susan Garrett, and Virginia and Cornelia's visit to Richmond
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1829 November 1 (Box 2)
  warns against the indulgence of regret, melancholy feelings, and the sentimentality of the past, encourages her to look to future opportunities and new experiences, and to enjoy the present, describes her move to a new house formerly occupied by John Rogers and his wife and its rooms and advantages
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge [1829?] (Box 2)
  describes her regret at the death of old Mrs. Coolidge, her social life in Washington, visits from the President's ladies, a Cabinet dinner at Martin Van Buren's home, the goodness of Burwell Randolph to the family, details of their economy, near neighbors, and supplies news concerning Ben at the University and Lewis working with Judge Carr
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1830 January 10 (Box 2)
  warns her not to allow the girls to attend too many parties as "they will render themselves cheap by so doing, exhaust their popularity and diminish their respectability," suggests ways of saving family time while forced to entertain visitors, mentions the marriage of Mrs. Humphrey and a Polish adventurer, Count Walewsky, and the somberness of Boston due to the failure of business
- Joseph Coolidge to Jefferson Randolph 1830 February 10 (Box 2)
  writes concerning his business interests, having dissolved his partnership with [Thomas] Bulfinch and striking out on his own, he asks Jeff if he could direct consignments of Southern produce to his business, such as flour, cotton and other products, because he plans to extend his business to include more than manufactured goods
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1830 March 14 (Box 2)
  discusses the surprising remarriage of Charles Lewis Bankhead, and the son of Dr. Warren who was shipped off to France after he stabbed an associate in a drunken brawl
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1830] April 2 (Box 2)
  sends a brief notification of her impending visit accompanying Susan and Thomas Coolidge
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1830 May 30 (Box 2)
  furnishes details of the death of their old nurse, Mammy Priscilla, her confusion over politics in Washington, and the lack of enough stages and steamboats to serve the needs of Congressmen leaving Washington
- Martha Randolph to Mrs. Coolidge, Sr. 1830 June 1 (Box 2)
  (Typescript Copy) expresses her enjoyment of the visit of Susan Coolidge and invites her to come as often as she likes
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1830 June 6 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the absence of her nursemaid Mrs. Cox, the increased load of work, her illness from pregnancy, the unpleasantness of Washington in the summer months, her scorn for Frances Wright who is again troubling Boston "where she divides public attention with a rhinoceros the first ever brought to the United States," a personal acquaintance of Ellen's, Wright's doctrine is said to be "for the happiness of both parties a preliminary step to the civil contract of marriage should be to live a year or two together without the contract"
- Joseph Coolidge to Jefferson Randolph 1830 August 26 (Box 2)
  discusses business matters, the birth of twin boys, Algernon and Sydney, the presence of Martha as a great comfort, and praises George for his many good qualities
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1830 October 15 (Box 2)
  writes concerning the plan of Martha to return to Washington in November, her suffering with the birth of the twins, George's intention of returning with Martha, indecision over the naming of the infants, securing a wet-nurse from the countryside, how to make do with fewer servants, "where there are slaves it is no matter how much work you make there are always plenty of people all the better for having something to do."
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1830 December 5 (Box 2)
  describes how much the whole household and other friends miss her presence, especially little Ellen, who dictated a letter to her mother to be included in this letter
- Martha Coolidge to Ellen Coolidge 1830 December 5 (Box 2)
  notifies her of her safe arrival in Washington, and of news that Dabney [Overton?] was killed in the battle for Algiers
- Joseph and Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1830] December 9 (Box 2)
  writes concerning Jared Sparks, his history of the United States and proposed biography of General George Washington and asks Martha to write a letter of introduction to Mrs. Gouverneur Morris to allow Sparks to use her husband's papers in his research
- Martha Randolph to Joseph Coolidge 1830 December 15 (Box 2)
  informs him that she has written a letter of introduction for Mr. Sparks and sent it to New York, by placing Gouverneur Morris in the ranks of America's great patriots she hopes to appeal to Mrs. Morris pride in her husband's accomplishments and convince her to allow Sparks access to her papers, Nicholas is in high favor with the President, and her worries about little Jefferson's hearing problems
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 February 22 (Box 3)
  reports that little Jefferson is dangerously ill, describes the routine of the house, the inconvenience of being without closets or furniture, the crowded condition of the house with eight grown-ups, two sickly children, and few servants, the receipt of a letter from Mrs. [Gouverneur] Morris concerning Jared Spark's request, plans for George's future include attending the University and entering a naval career, refers to a paragraph in the Telegraph about a bill for the financial relief of Martha proposed by [Senator George ?] Poindexter and the uproar it caused, describes [Henry ?] Middleton of South Carolina who had just returned from Russia, and mentions a thermometer and an Oliver Cromwell [portrait?]
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1831 March 7 (Box 3)
  sends news of her growing family, especially the progress of Ellen, and mentions Mr. Sparks thanks for Martha's letter of introduction to Mrs. Morris
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 March 8 (Box 3)
  informs her that Mr. Bailey will bring Joseph the thermometer and Oliver Cromwell [painting?], and notes that Poindexter's bill proposes a grant of land to Martha which may be easier for Congress to pass than a grant of money
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1831?] March 11 (Box 3)
  mentions the visit of Mrs. S.P. Gardner who will carry her letter to Washington, and songs that interest her
- Martha Randolph 1831 April 1 (Box 3)
  writes that George has secured a position in the navy on the John Adams for a three year voyage, due to a suggestion by John Nicholas, and that Ben had almost completed his coursework, and was urged to apply for a position of surgeon in the navy
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 April 23 (Box 3)
  describes their hasty preparations for George's departure on his three year naval voyage to the Mediterranean and Constantinople, and plans for Ben to get a surgeon position
- Cornelia Randolph 1831 May 10 (Box 3)
  informs her of their receipt of letters from George, his progress in the navy, their plans to leave for Edgehill on the 25th, news of President Jackson's appointment of Nicholas Trist as his private secretary, and the reconstruction of his Cabinet especially the unwilling resignations of Samuel D. Ingham and John Branch
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 May 18 (Box 3)
  warns her not to speak about Nicholas' appointment, shares the family's opinion of Andrew Jackson as "no common man, he has character and decision enough to do anything however great; his talents the war proved; etc." and also shares two anecdotes concerning Jackson's affection for his wife and his loyalty to his physician
- Ellen Coolidge to Virginia Trist 1831 June 19 (Box 3)
  tells her that her girls are now in school, that she has not heard from her mother or sisters for a month, and describes her enjoyment of [Ebenezer] Henderson's (1784-1858) Tour Through Iceland
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 June 21 (Box 3)
  apologizes for her delay in writing, mentions George's receipt of Ellen's letter, her thankfulness for President Jackson help in securing George's berth on the John Adams, reveals that [George] Poindexter's has told Jefferson of his plan to secure a township of 50,000 acres of land from Congress for Martha with the President locating the grant in several different localities to make the tracts easier to sell, describes her plans of dividing the land (if the bill is passed) in twelve shares with two for herself and one apiece for her children, and her plans for Monticello, describes her visit to the University and Albemarle County, and the condition of Monticello
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 June 29 (Box 3)
  furnishes a summary of the financial status of the family, and writes concerning the chance to sell Monticello to Dr. [James T.] Barclay, a Charlottesville druggist, the $30,000 of Thomas Jefferson's debts remaining to be paid, no income as yet from the publication of Thomas Jefferson's manuscripts, her dream of returning to Monticello to live, the hope of Congress donating land to Martha, the hostility in Virginia towards anything Jeffersonian where Jefferson's "principles are considered as having gone out of fashion," their dissatifaction with their house in Washington, her attitude toward the system of slavery, the prospects of her brothers Ben, Lewis, and James, Nicholas with the President at Old Point, and Browse Trist's appointment as Surveyor General of Louisiana
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 July 22 (Box 3)
  describes the meeting of the Board of Visitors at the University, the procedure of the public day which closes the session at the University of Virginia, its events, the graduation of Ben as a doctor, the outstanding University student of the year was Edwin Randolph, her enjoyment of the Virginia mountain scenery, mentions a person interested in purchasing Monticello, and Jefferson's accident when a horse kicked him in the knee
- George W. Randolph to Ellen Coolidge [1831] July 26 (Box 3)
  describes his visit to the ruins of Pompeii and Herculaneum near Naples while on his naval tour of duty, which Ellen sends on to her mother [October 3]
- Ellen Coolidge 1831 August 7 (Box 3)
  writes concerning a week at the summer resort of Nahant, Massachusetts and describes its inhabitants, her vacation, and acquaintainces, wishes that Monticello might be sold so that her mother would no longer hope to live there, and expresses her bitterness towards Virginia for its treatment of her grandfather and his family
- Martha Randolph to Ellen Coolidge [1831?] August 15 (Box 3)
  mentions her visit to the Dunglisons and the University for ten days during the meeting of the Board of Visitors, the graduation of Ben and his first successful operation, his desire to attend the medical lectures in Philadelphia, Lewis' disgust with his profession of law and his mother's hope of securing for him a clerkship, the sale of Monticello and 500 acres of land to Dr. Barclay, retaining family rights to the graveyard, and Edwin Randolph's success at the University
- Joseph Coolidge to Virginia Trist [1831] August 26 (Box 3)
  announces the birth of Thomas Jefferson Coolidge
- Cornelia Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 August 28 (Box 3)
  writes concerning the plans for the family to return to Washington in mid-October, the need for a larger house there, her regret over the sale of Monticello, Dr. Barclay's plans for Monticello, a final visit to Monticello when Virginia comes to [Edgehill?], the desire of the family to leave the slave states, her own feelings re slavery, her reaction to news of Nat Turner's Rebellion in Southampton County, Virginia, the disappointment with the work of Lewis at the University, and their hopes of getting him a clerkship
- Joseph Coolidge to Martha Randolph [1831] August 28 & 30 (Box 3)
  announces the birth of Thomas Jefferson Coolidge, reflects upon the rapid growth of his family, asks Ben to attend the medical lectures at Boston, and to stay with them, and refers to the Nat Turner Rebellion
- Mary Randolph to Ellen Coolidge 1831 September 25 (Box 3)
  expresses her sympathy with her sister over her rapid production of so large a family in so short a time, sends news of Ben who is presently living with Dr. Gilmer and assisting him with his patients in order to familiarize himself with the medicines necessary in an active practice, mentions James's attempts to continue to farm on a small scale and the necessity of building himself a new log house since his old home was located on the 500 acres purchased by Barclay, describes the fear generated by the "Southampton tragedy," and her hopes that the event will spur Virginia on to eradicate the evil of slavery
- Ellen Coolidge to Martha Randolph 1831 September 25 (Box 3)